# 大家好 現在天晴啦
Hi everyone! It's sunny now.
# 我上山上看一下有沒有那個野果
So I'm heading onto the hill and see if there are any, any wild fruits.
# 摘來吃一下啊
You could pick some.
# 你看 這是我們村
Look! This is an orchard,
# 有一位老爺爺 他自己種的那個果園哦
of an old man in our village. He planted everything, all by himself.
# 這個 茶樹
This is, tea tree.
# 這個 還有這個是
This is, and this is,
# 這個是牛頭柑 就是那個柚子啊
this is "bull head mandarin", which is actually pomelo.
# 我們叫柚子樹 這樣
We call it pomelo tree, yea.
# 還有茘枝樹
There are also lychee trees,
# 桃樹
peach trees,
# 李樹
plum trees,
# 還有板栗
and chestnuts too.
# 好多哇
A lot!
# 我記得還小的時候 他就在這裡種
I remember that when I was a kid, he was planting,
# 種了好多這個果樹
planting a lot of these fruit trees.
# 以前我還小的時候都來這裡摘過
I've also come and picked some fruits here when I was a kid,
# 趁他不在的時候
of course, when he was not around.
# 現在他又從新種了一下
And how he has planted some new ones,
# 種得更靚啦
which are much more beautiful.
# 你看 他這個
Look! This is ah,
# 這個柚子 柚子樹都開花啦
this is pomelo. The pomelo tree has already blossomed.
# 好多那些花 小花啊
There are a lot of flowers, small flowers.
# 到時候就有柚子摘啦
We can come again for the pomelos later.
# 你看 那裡還有桃花
Look! There are peach flowers too.
# 這個桃花就靚哦 (註︰很靚表達「就」這個概念，所以用了高一層次的字)
These peach flowers are gorgeous.
# 你看
Look!
# 這桃花
The peach flowers,
# 它顏色都不一樣的
they have different colours,
# 有的鮮艷一點 有的白一點
some are brighter, while some are paler.
# 可能品種不一樣
Perhaps they're of different specie.
# 你看 這房子還是用泥磚做的哦
Look! This house is still made of mudbrick.
# 很結實的哦 這樣
It's really firm, you know.
# 還最吉老的辦法做的
This is the oldest way of building a house.
# 全是那個
These are all,
# 黃泥
mud,
# 用黃泥來做
made with mud.
# 用黃泥做的
It's made with mud.
# 搞到搞不掉 (註︰不明白，我想應該是用手擦後不會沾到手的意思吧)
It doesn't shed.
# 做這個房子也不容易呀
Building this house is certainly not a simple task.
# 這從那裡
You need to, from there,
# 把家裡 要從 要從家裡把它這個泥 挑過來
from home, I mean, you need to bring, bring the mudbricks all the way from home,
# 一塊一塊挑過來
one after the other.
# 這裡可以打造成一個世外桃源
This place can be made a heaven on earth.
# 又有房子
There is a house.
# 有柵欄 再養小狗小雞
There are sheds. You can keep some doggies and chicks here,
# 摘點小鴨子在下面
and also some duckies down there,
# 再摘條小牛
and a calf too.
# 哇 這個地方很 很漂亮的哦
Wa! This place is rea, really pretty.
# 可能是那個 我們村的那個老爺爺
Perhaps the, I mean the old man in our village,
# 他也喜歡
he also likes,
# 他也喜歡這種清靜的生活
he also likes this kind of peaceful life.
# 你看 他只種 種上果樹
Look! He has only planted, planted fruit trees.
# 甚麼樹的果樹都可以種一點
It doesn't really matter what kind of fruits.
# 你看 又可以放點香菇
Look! He can also plant some mushrooms.
# 在這裡很清靜的哦
It's really peaceful here.
# 空氣又好
The air is fresh,
# 全部都是植物
as it's surrounded by plants.
# 沒有水泥板的哦 這裡
Nothing is made of concrete here.
# 哇 多好哇 每天睡到自然醒
Wa! What a wonderful life! You can switch off our alarm every night.
# 想想就
It's really...
# 等我老啦 等我老了的時候 我也找個這樣地方
When I become an old man, when I become an old man, I'm also gonna find such a place,
# 清靜一下生活
to spend my days peacefully.
# 每天就是種點青 種種青菜呀
Everyday, I plant some veg, plant some veggies,
# 逗逗小狗哇
play with the doggies,
# 再找條小豬 溜溜小豬
and get a piggy, walk the piggy.
# 也好
Why not?
# 你看 樹上一個都沒有啦
Look! There's not even one in the tree.
# 地上我看到了一個
And I see one on the ground.
# 一個
One
# 有一點青的
It's a bit green.
# 哎 吃了再說
Ay! Let me finish it first.
# 就一個
Just one
# 等下我們去挖竹笋
Let's go to dig some bamboo shoots in a while.
# 嗯 可以喲
Um! Not bad!
# 挖一點竹笋回去
Let's dig some bamboo shoots.
# 來都來啦 不能空著手回去嘛 是不是
We're already here. We just can't get back home empty-handed, can we?
# 嗯
Um!
# 可以
Not bad
# 有點酸
It's a bit sour.
# 沒啦
No more?
# 就一個
Just one
# 啊 回去
Ah! Let's go back,
# 回去下面
go back down there,
# 再 往那邊走
and, go that way.
# 現在去挖竹笋
We're now gonna dig some bamboo shoots.
# 鋤頭沒帶
I don't have a hoe today.
# 用刀來挖 用刀來挖
I'll dig with the knife, dig with the knife.
# 應該也能挖一點
I think I can still get some.
# 啊 這裡有
Ah! Here's one,
# 又檢了一個
one more.
# 這個就好吃的 這個
This one is undoubtedly tasty.
# 哎呀 可以 沒壞
Aya! Good! It's not rotten.
# 嗯
Um!
# 真好吃
It's really tasty!
# 這個很甜哦 這個
It's really sweet, you know.
# 剛剛青的
That one was green.
# 沒啦
No more
# 你看 從這裡進去
Look! We go this way.
# 這是竹林
This is a bamboo forest.
# 我們去這裡面去 可以
We get in from this way, then we can,
# 挖得到竹笋
find the bamboo shoots.
# 你看 這野芭蕉哦
Look! These are wild plantains.
# 這個野芭蕉
These wild plantains,
# 現在那麼大啦
look, they're already that big now.
# 它這個不 不 不 不把它砍掉的話也會那個的
Even if I don't, don't, don't chop it down, it would still, you know,
# 也會自然會死掉的
it would still die naturally.
# 我把它 砍下來
Let me, chop it down.
# 你看 這個很大了哦
Look! This is already that big.
# 可以砍啦
So I can chop it.
# 這個香蕉長出來之後哇 要把這個樹要砍掉 (註︰他又香蕉又芭蕉，我不管了，照字面譯)
The tree needs to be chopped down when there are bananas.
# 不然這個樹沒用的
It's useless keeping the tree here.
# 那麼大的樹
It's such a big tree.
# 你看 這個不是很靚哦 那個有個很靚的
Look! This is not really that beautiful. There's a really beautiful one.
# 又大
And big too
# 我砍那棵
I'll get that one.
# 我聽說這個芭蕉芘可以吃的哦
I've heard that the cores of the plantain trees are edible.
# 我怎麼敢吃
How would I dare to eat?
# 看一下
Let me take a look,
# 劈開來看一下
take a look inside.
# 好多那個水分啊 這裡
It's really juicy, here.
# 是不是可以吃的
Is it really edible?
# 哇 這個好像是誒
Wa! I think it's this part.
# 很嫩哦
It's really tender.
# 哇 就剩下這一坨
Wa! Only this little bit remains.
# 是不是能不能吃 (註︰這個有點混亂，也翻譯得混亂一點以配合吧)
Isn't it not edible or not?
# 誒呀
Yeeya!
# 不知道甚麼味
I can't describe the taste.
# 感覺甚麼味都沒有
It's like simply tasteless.
# 嗯 還是不要吃啦 算啦
Um! Forget it. I'm not eating it.
# 你看 這個香蕉
Look! The bananas,
# 這個香蕉就很靚的哦 香蕉
the bananas are really beautiful, the bananas.
# 把它帶回去
Lets' bring them back.
# 這邊全是那個野芭蕉哦
These are all the wild plantains here.
# 這沒人要的
They don't belong to anyone.
# 不知道是誰種的 種下去可能就是
I wonder who planted them. They were planted and then,
# 沒有 沒有 沒有去管啦
no, no, nobody takes care of them.
# 長得到處都是
So they're growing everywhere.
# 你看 下面有竹子哦 我下去看一下
Look! I see bamboos down there. Let me go down and have a look.
# 看一下有沒有
Let me see if there are any,
# 有沒有竹笋
any bamboo shoots,
# 竹笋
bamboo shoots.
# 你看 這裡有一個
Look! Here's one!
# 裂開的
It's cracked here.
# 啊 沒帶鋤頭
Ah! No hoe.
# 要有鋤頭我兩下就把它 挖到啦
If I had a hoe, I could be able to dig it out in a couple of seconds.
# 哎喲 好大哦
Ayo! It's really big!
# 好大哦
It's so big!
# 看到沒有
Can you see it?
# 這個應該大 這個
It should be a big one, definitely.
# 這一個就夠一晚上吃啦
This one alone is enough for a dinner.
# 這個不好挖
I don't think I can make it.
# 拔根棍來
Let me get a stick,
# 拔根棍來挖
and dig with a stick.
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 那麼硬的 這個
It's so hard!
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 很大 這個
This one is really large.
# 摘小一點的我也不介意呀
I won't mind having a smaller one.
# 搞那麼大的給我幹嘛
So why do you give me such a big one?
# 沒帶鋤頭
Without a hoe,
# 就是不好挖
things become so much more difficult.
# 剛好兄弟來啦 借他的鋤用一下
I just saw my buddy. Let me borrow a hoe from him.
# 這個很大的
This one is really big.
# 拿頭鋤頭來
Give me your hoe!
# 夠大 這個
It's big enough.
# 哪個
Which one?
# 很深
It's so deep.
# 還沒我挖的那個大
It's not even as big as the one that I dug.
# 你挖的有多大
How big is yours then?
# 好有很多
There are still a lot.
# 很深的 有的挖都挖不到
Some are really deep that you can't even dig them up.
# 是
Indeed
# 不要挖爛了就很靚 挖爛了就沒意思了
It's really beautiful, if I don't break it. It would be too bad if I do.
# 要挖寬一點
Dig wider!
# 還刀一到 (註︰不明白)
Not yet.
# 莖都還沒有挖到 (註︰笋的莖又是甚麼意思？我照字面譯算了)
You haven't even reached the stem.
# 很難挖
It's really hard.
# 去哪裡挖來 是不是去裡面
Where is it? Is it inside?
# 去裡面
Yes, inside.
# 太多雜草 找都不好找
These's too much weed, making it very difficult to find one.
# 年底就10塊錢一斤
It was 10 RMB/500 g by the end of last year.
# 現在有2塊錢都值
It still costs 2 RMB now.
# 2塊錢沒人會去挖
No one would be digging it for 2 RMB.
# 好深呀 這個
It's really deep, here.
# 這個竹笋最少3斤
This bamboo shoot is at least a kilogram and a half.
# 哇 這個
Wa! This is...
# 這個 沒找到
this one...I've not yet
# 它的頭在哪
Where's its head?
# 全都是根
There are only roots.
# 你很專用[SIC]挖這個 是不是
You're professional in it, aren't you?
# 看你挖弓好多在上面
I saw that you had dug a lot up there.
# 無從下刀
There's nowhere to cut it out.
# 鋤頭
Hoe...
# 哇
Wa!
# 扁的
It's flat.
# 我還以為
I though it was...
# 圓的才俊
A round one is more handsome.
# 對
Exactly!
# 可以 這個
Alright! This is,
# 可以搞一餐啦
enough for a meal.
# 今天晚上就
Tonight I'll,
# 用它來炒咸菜
fry it with pickled mustard.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 去回去啦
We need to go back.